<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Behaviour of Mr. Will. Staley in Newgate after his condemnation for high-treason : with the substance of his last speech and discourses at the usual place of execution, whither being drawn on a sledge he was hang'd and quarter'd there, on Tuesday the 26th of this instant November, 1678.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1709A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09288500</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09288500</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27273)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1301:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Behaviour of Mr. Will. Staley in Newgate after his condemnation for high-treason : with the substance of his last speech and discourses at the usual place of execution, whither being drawn on a sledge he was hang'd and quarter'd there, on Tuesday the 26th of this instant November, 1678.</title>
                  <author>Staley, William, d. 1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.G.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Staley, William, d. 1678.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42621:1"/>
            <p> THE BEHAVIOUR OF Mr. Will. Staley IN NEWGATE, After his Condemnation for High-Treaſon.</p>
            <p>With the ſubſtance of his laſt SPEECH and DISCOURSES at the uſual place of Execution,</p>
            <p>Whither being drawn on a Sledge, he was Hang'd and Quarter'd there,</p>
            <p>On Tueſday the 26th of this inſtant <hi>November.</hi> 1678.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>LICENSED, 1678.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. G.</hi> 1678.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42621:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42621:2"/>
            <head>The Behaviour OF Mr. Will. Staley IN NEWGATE After CONDEMNATION.</head>
            <p>COncerning the Tryal of this Perſon, Care hath already been taken by Authority, to have a full and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Account made publique; whereby it will appear, for what Horrid and Treaſonable words againſt the Sacred Life and Perſon of the Beſt of Kings, his Maieſty, our moſt Gracious Sovereign; and upon what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42621:3"/> full and clear Evidence, and fair Hearing, the Priſoner was Convicted, and Condemned to be Drawn, Hanged, and Quartered. After which dreadful Sentence he was carried back from <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> to <hi>Newgate,</hi> from whence he came, having time allowed him from that <hi>Thurſday</hi> to the <hi>Tueſday</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to fit and prepare himſelf for that great and terrible Change. As his Education had been in the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Profeſſion, and (as 'tis ſaid) amongſt the moſt dangerous of that Party, I mean the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> beyond the Seas; ſo he did not ſtick to own himſelf a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick: However, Mr. Ordinary, according both to his Office and Chriſtian inclinations to take all opportunities for the good of Souls, went ſeveral times to viſit him, and offer his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Aſſiſtances; whom he received with much reſpect, deſiring him to come as often as he could; who failed not therein, but uſed the moſt preſſing Arguments, as well to bring him to a ſenſe of the deteſtable hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of the Crime for which he was to ſuffer, and other his Sins; as alſo to take him off from the Errors and Superſtitions of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42621:3"/> Popiſh Church; not to flatter himſelf with any previous Diſpenſations, or ſubſequent Pardon from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any of its Prieſts, or of any Prayers or Offices that might be ſaid for him after Death, for that all thoſe things would prove wholly vain and uſeleſs to his Soul, when it ſhould approach the Divine Tribunal, where nothing would ſtand him in ſtead, but only the Merits of our Lord Jeſus, and to be cloathed with his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: that he having but a few Minutes left to ſecure his Eternal Condition, it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore behoved him with all his might, to lay hold on that Rock of Ages, by caſting away all ſuperſtitious Conceits, and getting a true and lively Faith, ſo as not to put any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Men or Angels, but in Chriſt alone. To come out from a people of Blood, and not ſuffer them to deſtroy his Soul too by the in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, who had been the occaſion of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Body to an ignominious deſtruction. To conſider the excellency of true Proteſtant Principles, as founded on the un-erring Word of God, and not on the uncertain Traditions
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42621:4"/> of Men, and incomparably beyond any others, moſt advancing the grand deſignes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, <hi>viz.</hi> Glory to God, Peace on Earth, and Good will towards Men. Whereas the Tenets which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath added, are derogatory to Gods honor, Chriſts merits, full of Superſtition and Idolatry, deſtructive to Government and Society, invented only to ſerve Ambition or Covetouſneſs, without any footſteps in Holy Scripture, and never owned in the Primitive Church for ſeveral hundred years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such and the like pious Exhortations (but much more at large and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically delivered) the Miniſter urged to him: which he heard with a becoming atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But returned not much in anſwer, ſave only frequent Sighs, and ſometimes ſhort private ejaculations.</p>
            <p>Indeed after his Condemnation, he was all along very reſerv'd in words, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemious as to Drink or Victuals, eating very little, and ſpent the laſt night almoſt wholly at his Devotions.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42621:4"/>
            <p> On Tueſday the 26th inſtant, between Ten and Eleven of the Clock, he was brought out and put upon the Sledge, drawn with four Horſes, in which being ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he lay leaning on the ſtraw with his back, and ſometimes raiſed himſelf and ſat up. He had on a very good Black Suit, a becoming Perriwig, and Silk Stockings; but his Hat he put not on. His Countenance was grave and compoſed, expreſſing by the elevation of his Hands and Eyes, and motion of his Lips, very frequent marks of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Through all the way he was attended with a very extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Guard; ſo many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, Watchmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the like has not for many years bin ſeen.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42621:5"/>
            <p> Being come to <hi>Tyburn</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place of Execution, he did not ſtand to make any formal Speech; but in ſeveral diſcourſes, though he did not abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the words, ſeemed willing to have extenuated his Guilt, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging that he had no Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Intention, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> However, he pray'd very fervently, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be attentive to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the Miniſter; and ſo begging very heartily all good people to pray for him, he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Sentence, and was H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng'd and Quarter'd, many people pittying his perſon, but all acknowledging the Juſtice of his puniſhment, and deteſting his Traiterous Crime.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42621:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
